This is our planet
's final frontier
An inner world
where only the
most adventurous dare to go
Beneath our feet
are countless
miles of cave shafts and passages
The cave of
swallows in Mexico
400 metres
to the bottom
Deep enough to
engulf the Empire State Building
This is the
biggest cave shaft in the world
Yet these depths
were first explored
Only two years
before men landed on the moon
Today
caves remain the
least explored places on Earth
However
human beings are
seldom the first
to reach
these black
damp places
Here live some of
the strangest and least known animals
on the planet
This galaxy of
little lights
is created by
thousands of living creatures
Any animal that
lives in a cave
has to cope with
complete blackness
But in New Zealand
some have turned
this darkness to their advantage
A silken strand
is lowered from the ceiling
alongside
hundreds of others
Beautiful though
these threads are
they have a
sinister purpose
This is a
cave glowworm
To trap its prey
it goes fishing
with a
line of silk
The silk comes
from glands in the glowworm's mouth
and is loaded
with droplets of mucus
Each glowworm
produces dozens of these threads
Once its
lines are set
the glowworm
hangs from a mucus hammock
and waits
like a
patient angler
But the glowworm
doesn't leave everything to chance
That ghostly blue light
is the result of
a chemical reaction
Taking place
inside a special capsule in its tail
The light literally shines out of its backside
It's a lure for
attracting prey
Insects seem
irresistibly drawn towards the source
And then get
trapped by the sticky lines
Once stuck
there is no escape
Now
it's just a
matter of reeling in the line
and slowly
consuming the catch
alive
By ensnaring the
insects that hatch in this cave
these glowworms
have solved the biggest challenge
that permanent
cave dwellers face
Finding a regular
and reliable source of food
One kind of rock
makes this whole underground world possible
Limestone
Most of the world'
s caves are found within it
And it covers
nearly 10% of the Earth's surface
Limestone is composed of minerals derived from marine shells and corals
So although this
rocky escarpment in the United States
is now hundreds
of metres above sea level
It was actually
formed underwater
The limestone
towers of Vietnam's Ha Long Bay
are a reminder
of this link with the sea
Originally
this whole area
would have been one solid block of limestone
The base of
a coral reef
In Borneo
rain has sculpted
the limestone into extremely sharp sided pinnacles
But the dissolving power of rainwater
has other
much more
dramatic effects underground
Rivers that
flow over limestone
often seem to
completely disappear
When the water
reaches a more resistant bed of limestone
Its course
is halted
Once underground
the water
takes on a new
more erosive power
During its
journey from the surface
the water absorbed carbon dioxide from the soil
making it
mildly acidic
And over
millions of years
this acid eats
away the limestone
creating a maze
of caverns and passages
That sometimes
go on for miles
This is the biggest underground river passage in the world
So big
a jumbo jet
could fly through it
It's Deer
Cave in Borneo
The sheer size of Deer Cave allows some animals to gather there in huge numbers
A staggering three million wrinkledlipped bats live here
The bats roost
high on the walls and ceilings
Where they're
well protected from the outside elements
And safe
from predators
And while
they're up here
the bats produce
something very important
This hundred metre high mound is made entirely of bat droppings
guano
Its surface is
covered by a thick carpet of cockroaches
Hundreds of
thousands of them
Caves are one of
the few habitats on Earth
not directly
powered by sunlight
In the
absence of plants
this food
chain is based
on a continuous supply
of bat droppings
The cockroaches
feed on the guano
and anything
that falls into it
The droppings
also support other types of cockroaches
which spend part
of their day resting on cave walls
These in
turn become food
for giant
cave centipedes
some more than
20 centimetres long
Bizarrely
there are
crabs here too
sifting through
the droppings for nutrients
All these animals
spend their entire lives within the cave
They're totally
dependent on the digested remains of food
That's brought
in from outside
Each evening
in just two hours
three million
bats leave the safety of the cave
to hunt for
insects in the forest outside
But not all
will return
As they
leave the cave
the stream of
bats form a doughnutshaped ring
The wheeling bats
seem to confuse a rufousbellied eagle
But they must
still survive the attacks of other
more specialised birds of prey
Peregrine
falcons and bat hawks
are the jet
fighters of the bird world
Good hunting will
end as the light fades
So the bat hawks
bolt their catches on the wing
And flies
straight back for more
Any bat separated from the group
becomes a clear
and obvious target
And is
asking for trouble
Yet
the nightly onslaught has little impact on bat numbers
By the morning
the vast majority
will be back in
the safety of the cave
Bats are not the
only commuters in these morning caves
There's a day
shift as well
Returning from
hunting in the sunlight
These commuters
rely on their loud clicks
To find their way
through the cave passages
In total darkness
They're
cave swiftlets
Like bats
they use
echolocation to navigate
We need lights to
see what's going on
But in the
pitch black
the swiftlets
manage unerringly
to locate their
individual nesting sites
Which are only a
few centimetres across
It's a
remarkable skill
and one we still
do not fully understand
These birds are
unusual for another reason
Their little cuplike nests are made entirely from threads of saliva
It takes more
than 30 days to complete one
The nests are
very precious objects
and not only
for the birds
阿桑…
It's a very
risky business
With virtually no
safety equipment
and using ladders
made from forest vines
The gatherers climb into the highest reaches of the cave
Often more than
60 metres from the floor
The work may be
hazardous in the extreme
But the
rewards are great
The pure whiteness of cave swiftlets
Are the main
ingredient of bird's nest soup
And gram for gram
Are worth as
much as silver
As soon as its
nest is removed
a bird will
immediately build another
So
as long as its
valuable harvest is properly controlled
The colonies will
continue to flourish
唔好啊，小北，唔好啊，小北…
唔好啊
But water in
caves doesn't only erode
it also builds
This water is
loaded with dissolved limestone
And when it meets
the air in the cave
Some of that is
deposited as a mineral
calcite
As it builds up
so the calcite
forms decorations that hang from the ceiling
stalactites
Each drop leaves
behind only a minuscule amount of calcite
But over time
the process can
produce some spectacular results
If the water
seeps through the ceiling quickly
then the calcite
is deposited on the floor of the cave
And that
creates stalagmites
Variations in
water flow and air currents
produce an
infinite variety of forms
but all are
created by the same process
The slow deposition of dissolved limestone
And when stalactite meets stalagmite
a column is born
Structures like
these in North America's Carlsbad Cavern
can take many
thousands of years to develop
But sometimes
the formations in
a cave stop growing altogether
These flooded
caves in Mexico
have remained
virtually unchanged for thousands of years
Since the
last ice age
they've become
cut off from the outside world
Yet their impact
on life at the surface
has been huge
500 years ago
they supported
one of the world's great civilisations
the Maya
Mexico's
Yucatan Peninsula
has no rivers
lakes or streams
So the Maya
relied on the cenotes
the flooded
entrances to the waterfilled caves
These
flooded shafts
are the region's
only source of open freshwater
The cenotes
are in effect
gigantic
freshwater wells
Away from the
lifegiving rays of sunshine
One might not
expect to find plants
But in the
darkness of the cave tunnels
roots of giant
tropical trees
have pushed their
way through cracks in the limestone
to reach the
flooded caverns
Without this water
the Yucatan's
forest could not grow so luxuriantly
The Maya knew
that their lives depended on this water
But it's only
with the help of today's technology
That we've come
to appreciate the full significance and scale
Of these
flooded passageways
So far
more than 350 miles of underwater galleries in the Yucatan have been mapped
But still
nobody yet knows
the true extent of this subterranean water world
And with
good reason
Underwater caving
is notoriously dangerous
When the nearest
exit may be hundreds of metres or more away
Running out of
air down here would be fatal
To avoid
getting lost
Divers carry with
them a spool of string
It becomes
their lifeline
literally
The string also
doubles as a measuring tape
A technique that
has been used here in Mexico
To chart the
largest underwater cave in the world
All 100
miles of it
Cave exploration
often requires you
to push yourself
through narrow gaps in the rock
Cavers call such
places "squeezes"，The tighter the squeeze
the greater the
chance of damaging some vital
life
support system
In these
conditions
a diver could
easily become disorientated
and that
could be fatal
The flooded caverns can play tricks on you in other ways
What
seems like air
isn't
It's just
another kind of water
This is a
halo cline
a meeting of
fresh and salt water
Fresh water from the jungle flows over the heavier salt water from the sea
The saltwater
layer is extremely low in oxygen
making it a particularly difficult place for animals to live
Yet some
have managed it
like the remipede
one of the most
ancient of all living crustaceans
The Maya understood the importance of the cenotes
But they could never have known that these flooded passageways
were actually the
beginning of subterranean rivers
All of which
eventually flow out to the sea
Saltwater
unlike freshwater
does not
erode limestone
So most sea caves
are created by
the mechanical pounding of the waves
The rocky outcrops of New Zealand's poor night islands
are riddled
with sea caves
and just like
those in Borneo
they have become
important shelters for many species
After a day
feeding in the open water
vast shoals of
demoiselle fish
return to
the caves
which they use as
a refuge from predators
For these fish
the caves are a
nighttime retreat
But they're not
the only commuters in here
There are other
fish working to a different schedule
The big eyes are
the equivalent of bats
Night feeders
that leave the cave each evening
And like all
cave commuters
they are
most vulnerable
at the scheduled
time of departure
A bottleneck funnels these exiting bats into dense concentrations
attracting the
attention of others
The bats can
detect the snakes using echolocation
But the snakes
are literally in the dark
they can
see nothing
The strikes seem
to be largely hit and miss
But the snakes
have a secret weapon
They can actually
sense each bat flying past
Receptors in
the snake's head
Pick up the heat
given off by the flying bats
As this
thermal image shows
To the snakes
the bats are
apparently glowing
and this gives
them something to aim at
This is the price
that these cave commuters must pay
for their
daytime sanctuary underground
Small wonder then
that there are
other cave dwellers that stay put
Many caves
are like islands
cut off from
the outside world
and from
other caves
This isolation
has resulted in
the evolution of some very strange creatures
They are the
cave specialists
troglobites
animals that never emerge from the caves or see daylight
These troglodytes from Thailand
are possibly the
most specialised creatures on Earth
For they live
only in cave waterfalls
The entire population of these cave angel fish
seems to be
restricted to just two small caves
It's the same
story with other troglodytes
There may well be
less than a hundred
Texas cave
salamanders in the wild
And the
Belizean white crab
is another creature
that is unique
to just one cave system
Living in
perpetual darkness
they have all not
only lost the pigment in their skin
but also
their eyes
It takes thousands of generations for eyes to be lost
So these species
must have been isolated
for a very
long time
But the blind salamander has other highly developed sensory organs
Receptors in the skin detect minute movements in the water made by its prey
External gills help it to breathe in water that is particularly low in oxygen
The cave angelfish feed on bacteria in the fastflowing water
Keeping their
grip with microscopic hooks on their fins
Food is often
in short supply
And troglodytes like the crab
Have to survive
on whatever washes into the cave from outside
A salamander might not encounter food for several months
So when something does come along
It can't
afford to miss it
It's astonishing that these extraordinary cave dwellers managed to survive at all
But one cave is
so inhospitable
that one would
not expect it to contain any life whatsoever
The water flowing
out of the Via Luce cave in Mexico
is actually
coloured white with sulphuric acid
Explorers
entering this dangerous cave
must wear respirators and carry monitors
Poisonous gases
rise to fatal levels so quickly
that an early
warning system is essential
Ats survive by
staying close to the skylights
But venturing
deep into the cave
is very
dangerous indeed
The source of these toxic fumes lies several miles below
Hydrogen sulphide gas bubbles out from oil deposits in the Earth's crust
It mixes with oxygen in the water and forms sulphuric acid
These are not the sort of conditions in which you would expect to find fish
Yet these cave
mollies seem to thrive
despite the acid
and the low levels of oxygen
There is in fact
more life here than anyone would think possible
But the biggest
surprise is something altogether more bizarre
These strange
stalactitelike formations
are known
rather
appropriately
as snotites
The drops
dripping from the ends
are
sulphuric acid
strong
enough to burn skin
The snotites are
in fact vast colonies of bacteria
capable of
growing a centimetre a day
In this world
without sunlight
these bacteria extract energy from the hydrogen sulphide gas
Bacteria like
these are known as extremophiles
Because of their
ability to survive in such extreme conditions
And these extremophiles play another important role in this cave
Surprisingly
they are the
basis of a food chain
Which supports
amongst other creatures
the larvae of
these midges
Via Lueh's ecosystem was certainly very remarkable
But cave explorers were soon to make an even more astonishing discovery
Beneath this arid
landscape lies a subterranean wonderland
Without water
one might not
expect to find any caves
But beneath these
rolling desert slopes in the United States
Lies one of
the longest
deepest
and most surprising caves in the world
Its secrets
remained unknown until 1986
When cavers dug
through several metres of loose rock
At the
bottom of this pit
They
named the cave
Leticia
And since
its discovery
More than 120
miles of passageways have been mapped
When the first
explorers descended
no one guessed at
the sheer size of this cave
But even that was
not going to be the biggest surprise
Little did they
realise that Lechuguilla
would soon be
regarded by cavers the world over
as the most
beautiful of all caves
They were
about to discover
some of the most
exquisite formations
ever seen
underground
The walls
were covered
with the most
delicate and fragile crystals
Many of these
crystals were made of gypsum
a mineral that
comes from limestone
And there was
mile after mile of them
Water is the
creator of most caves
But unlike all
other limestone caves
Lechuguilla's rock had not been eaten away by running rainwater
Something else
was responsible
The only water
Lechuguilla has
are these
wonderfully still
clear pools
As the explorers
went deeper into the cave
They came across
whole galleries
Filled with the
most unusual formations
Like these
five metre cones
Frosted with the
most delicate crystals
It was Lechuguilla
's gypsum crystals
That made scientists question how these caverns were formed
They discovered
that Lechuguilla's limestone
had actually been
eaten away by sulphuric acid
cutting through
literally miles of limestone
And when sulphuric acid dissolves limestone
it leaves
behind gypsum
the basis of
Lechuguilla's remarkable formations
And there
was one set
more than a mile
from the surface
that almost
defied belief